Good afternoon. Welcome to the Primary Production Select Committee.
We're scheduled 30 minutes,
so I'll leave it in your hands to start with.
I'm sure there'll be plenty of questions.
Brilliant. Kia ora, and thank you, Chair, members of the committee.
Delighted to be here today to follow up on your trip to
Marlborough in February last year.
Yes.
Provide an update on the New Zealand wine industry.
Very pleased to have with me today, Sarah Wilson, our general counsel.
Also Nicola Crinnan, our advocacy manager.
Happy to answer any questions, and also good timing because next week we'll be
releasing our annual report, which will provide a greater overview of the
state of the industry.
So, since I became CEO in July, I've spent
the last seven weeks going around talking to members,
visiting regions, going to forums, and obviously engaging with key
stakeholders.
And I've really appreciated that opportunity to hear directly from our members.
Those conversations have been frank, as I'm sure you're familiar with
conversations in our primary industries tend to be.
And I've appreciated the openness and the transparency.
It's fair to say there are challenges in
our industry, particularly for growers.
Our growers are having to make, and our members, difficult
decisions based on changing consumption patterns, based
on agricultural factors and commercial market issues.
As a result of those, they are considering what they do about their
vineyards, if they mothball them, if they sell them.
They are also making decisions about future investment.
So, there are a range of commercial decisions going on
at this moment. But if I think about it, what really strikes me from those
conversations is it's a theme of active adjustment.
This is not an industry in crisis. This is an industry responding to
circumstances, and those particular circumstances are supply, demand, and
balance.
Yeah.
So, as you may be aware, last vintage, 2025, was
one of the second largest on record, and it followed a number of
exceptionally large vintages. So, that has created
a surplus, which has taken some time to flow through.
And so our members are making the decisions in order to enable
that to be amortised.
What I am hearing is that that is improving.
Several of the larger wineries that I've spoken to, and some of the small, medium,
have said they expect to be in balance either next year or the year
after. Obviously, I can't extrapolate from that sample size, but they
are encouraging signs.
And I think what gives me confidence, moreover, is the broader
global context, where we are continuing to grow our
exports. Our exports grew 9% in the year
to June. They grew above the category in all our key
markets. If we're talking about Australia, UK,
US, China, Canada, they grew in value or
volume or both.
So, in a declining market, we are winning.
I think the other thing that's really important for us to remember is that this is
not and never will be about scale. We're 1% of the
world's wine. We have plenty of room to grow.
So, what helps us grow is our reputation, our
distinctiveness, our quality, and our sustainability credentials.
And those things rest, really, on the consumer.
And really, the consumer's perception is high.
We can see that via export growth, but we can also see that in the trends.
We're producing what our consumers want, which is lighter,
fresher, premium products based on authentic
stories and with strong credentials.
So, those two trends give me confidence in
where the industry is heading.
And when I have the conversations about challenges, they pivot
quite quickly to opportunities and people are talking about
innovation, and we talk about innovation in packaging formats, in
liquid development and perhaps in flavor profiles.
Talking about investments in technology.
Growers and wineries are embracing AI tools that are enabling them to be
more effective and efficient.
They're also looking at different techniques, and we're enabling that through
our research program, through the Bragato Research Institution.
They're looking at exploring new markets and obviously exciting
news on the India FTA, which we're going through yesterday,
that provides not an instant answer, but I think a platform for
long-term growth for the industry.
And we can match that along other exciting markets that our members are interested
in, like South Korea.
And the larger members also say that they've seen this cycle before.
This is not something that hasn't happened.
It hasn't happened in a while. And so the industry is continuing
to adjust its production mechanisms, its exports, and its markets to
meet that demand. And I'm confident that we will get supply and demand
back in balance
and continue to build on the strong future.
So, with those remarks, I'm very happy for myself or the team to take
any questions you might have.
Firstly, congratulations on the new role.
Thank you.
You're
filling in for a
long-serving
member who was there before you.
And thanks for the opportunity last year for that trip
around
various vineyards and
wineries in Marlborough. It was quite enlightening for a lot of us who
haven't had
a lot to do with the industry. So, that was really good.
Look, I guess the question is, there's a lot of
vineyards that are changing land use at the moment
throughout the country and/or just not
harvesting
grapes
How long do you think that can go on before
the industry really feels the effects of lower
supply and/or
an exit from the industry?
You're right. There is adjustment throughout the country, and that
adjustment is not always evenly spread by region,
by grower size, or by winery.
As I referenced, I think that we are starting to see the
signs of the light at the end of the tunnel, and whether that's next
year or the year after,
sorry, I'm not very good at the predictions.
But, and climatic factors can obviously play into it.
Vintage size will be an important indicator, again, of how
quickly the surplus washes through.
But I think that the hard decisions have likely already been
made or taken. The industry is adjusting fast.
And, I'm hopeful that we'll emerge all the stronger for it.
Because, sorry, I just need to follow up on that.
Sorry.
But profitability is a big part of it, isn't it?
And if
a lot that are contemplating their future-
Mm-hmm
... at the moment aren't profitable,
how long do you think they can, because there's quite a few, that-
Yeah
... have approached us that are
at break even or below at the moment, and it's a high
input system. So
how long do they think they could hang on for?
These are ongoing conversations that are happening kind of at the regional level
because, and does, to your point, play into what is the long-run sustainability,
what are the alternative land uses, what are the other
economic routes to market. So,
in Marlborough, as you might be aware, they had a land use forum recently
facilitated by the Marlborough District Council, very well attended.
And I think that's the thing that we as an industry and also the regional
stakeholders are trying to do, is give growers that opportunity, in particular,
to assess their options in this context and say where would
they like to go. Because it's not easy, and some
of them can weather it, and others are less well-positioned.
Rachel.
Thanks, Chair. Thank you. I've just got a different line of questioning, actually-
Sure
... which is around the impact of
the challenges in transport. And,
obviously,
yeah, useful to get the supply and demand briefing.
Mm.
But just in terms of the cost of transport, cost of fuel, but also wondering how
the new
Port Nelson facility's going in Marlborough and if that's,
you might not be across the full details of that, but
obviously that's a great innovation-
Mm
... that's designed to actually help with productivity.
So just wondering if there's a good news story there.
But also,
challenges around the Cook Strait ferries and cost of fuel, cost of
transport, whether that's also having an impact.
You're right that this is not something that I've looked at in any detail.
Some of our members, particularly Wineworks, have been helpful in giving some
baseline information because one of the questions I asked is kind of,
where are supply choke points? What is the impact of the cost of transportation?
I don't have any information here today, but I'd be very happy to follow up with
you on that.
Okay. Great. Yep.
Because particularly, Nelson is an important port for us.
Yep.
Staffing issues. You're happy with the ability
to
employ staff at the moment, particularly,
the RSE situation.
There's no
noise that I've heard of
coming from growers that they are struggling, but that
may not be the case. You'll enlighten us, please.
I haven't heard in my trips, certainly not to date,
about them struggling to get staff.
I think what I've really heard is about the value of the RSE scheme and
their desire to maintain continuity with those skilled workers who come
back year after year and provide a really valuable support for a job
that we can't replace with technology at the moment.
So we were very pleased to see the pragmatic reforms that were announced the other
day, things that will streamline the system and
hopefully help realize continued value.
But I think it provides an important outlet as part of the
broader primary sector between ourselves and other horticultural
industries as well.
But Nicola, is there anything that you would think of that I've missed?
Just that
we're really looking forward to next year.
It'll be 20 years of RSE, and I think it's something to be celebrated.
It's like a world-recognized circular migration scheme.
Mm-hmm.
And there's been some really good work done in terms of what the
Pacific countries and the people gain back
from the scheme itself.
Yeah.
The investment in them and the investment they're able to take back.
Professor Bedford has done an amazing study.
So we're really hoping that we'll be able to be part of the celebrations.
Very good.
I was going to ask about regulatory barriers.
Is there anything that
you find
a problem that could be easily fixed as far
as
government regulatory barriers go?
It was looking exciting till you added the word easily fixed.
Well-
From your view, yeah.
I think, we're engaging constructively around
things such as the freshwater farms, the
RMA. We talked to the minister yesterday about the
plant import requirements and review.
So those things are all of interest to us.
If I were to talk wearing the domestic member hat, I would say that
excise continues to be a significant burden on our industry.
Obviously, domestic market's important for our small-
Mm
... our local producers,
who depend on tourism, hospitality,
and often use us as a trial market and a route to larger markets and exports.
And they've seen
excise go up by 24% in the last few years.
That's a significant burden that they can't pass on at the moment because
of the trading conditions. So effectively, it's a tax on production.
So if there were any opportunity to pause
or reduce excise, I think that would be welcomed.
Currently, we would estimate that it's more expensive than the cost of grapes
per ton in terms of imports, so just to give you some perspective.
Yeah.
But I appreciate you did say easily, so.
Yeah. No, look, I guess
a number of
grape growers, brewers, and distillers have-
Mm-hmm
... certainly approached probably most of the MPs here about excise
in the last couple of years.
So, I guess it's good to have that
consistency.
Mm-hmm.
Any other questions?
Well, my shift used today.
And it was all very positive. Thank you.
Yeah. Look, thank you very much for your time today.
Thank you for the opportunity.
And, good luck.
Well, we certainly hope.
Yeah.
And I hope the season ahead's a better one for the growers. Yeah.
We all do. Thank you.
Thanks.